Mather & Platt Graphics 6773 G
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mather & Platt Graphics
1874-1885
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mather & Platt
6773 G
1 folders
1 file folder
Graphics.
Images of machinery made by Mather and Pratt in the late 19th century.
10064509
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 11, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 30, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Mather & Platt of Manchester, England, was formed in 1853 by the merger of two machinery building companies, one begun by Pete Mather in 1817 and the other, Salford Iron Works, begun by John and Thomas Sherratt in 1829 and later taken over by John Platt. Mather & Platt made textile machinery, steam engines, turbine pumps, dynamos, and other machinery.
Scope and Contents
Includes images of steam engines and other machinery built by Mather & Pratt during the late 19th century. Includes images of a turbine pump, dynamos, a boring machine, diagonal steam engines, a printing machine, and other machinery.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Boring machinery; Drying equipment industry; Electric power; Lighting; Linen; Napping machines; Steam-engines; Textile fabrics; Textile finishing; Textile machinery; Textile printing; Textile technology-General; Turbines; Mather & Platt.
10064509
- Steam engines and steam- and belt-driven machinery, 1874-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Mather's patent elastic finishing machine for sketching and drying textile fabrics., 1865; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Photomechanical print depicts image of woman sitting at large finishing machine circa 1865. 28 x 22 cm.
    Format: Graphics.
  - Item 2: Early six-colour textile printing machine with double cylinder diagonal steam engine., 1885; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts printing machine circa 1885. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 3: Electric light machinery. A double-cylinder diagonal steam engine driving a Manchester dynamo., 1878; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts steam engine driving dynamo circa 1878. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 4: Early light three-bowl friction calender used for imparting a superior finish upon the cloth., 1877; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    print depicts early calendering machine circa 1877. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 5: The Edison-Hopkinson Dynamo., 1885; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts the side and front views of the dynamo circa 1885. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 6: Mather's "Patent" Aniline Ageing and Steaming Chamber used for the fixing of colours upon cloth after printing., 1876; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print shows image of steaming chamber circa 1876. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 7: Raising Machine for raising the pile on Moleskins, Beavers, etc. to resemble natural skins., 1880; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts raising [napping] machine circa 1880. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 8: The Edison-Hopkinson Patent Slow-Speed Dynamo, driven direct by a Tower Spherical Engine., 1885; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts the dynamo circa 1885. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 9: Mather-Reynolds high-lift turbine pump driven by a Mather & Platt special direct-acting steam engine., 1885; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts turbine pump circa 1885. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 10: Mather's Patent High-Speed Spring Beetling Machine for the finishing of finest Sateens, Linenettes, Drills and White Shirtings., 1879; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts beetling machine circa 1879. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 11: Double-Cylinder Diagonal Steam Engine used for driving separate machines such as printing machines and calenders etc., 1878; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts diagonal steam engine circa 1878. 28 x 22 cm.
  - Item 12: Mather's Patent Earth and Rock Boring Machine for artesian borings and mineral explorations to any depth down to 3000 feet., 1874; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photomechanical print depicts boring machine with workmen circa 1874. 28 x 22 cm.